Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Is there anything wrong with my health?
Your Highness has consumed musk.
Musk?
Dr. Zhang told me that musk is forbidden in my palace.
Why would I use it?
But Your Highness's noble body shows signs of using musk.
It's a small amount, not easily noticeable.
I did not use it.
These days,
I have only been exposed to incense in one place.
Vermilion, go to the Household Department tomorrow
and try to get some Pleasancy incense.
Yes.
Your Highness has been unwell not only because of the miscarriage
but also unrestrained sadness.
The sadness caused stagnation of the five
organs, and deficient fire in the Liver.
This has created an imbalance in your emotions.
Good doctors can treat physical illnesses,
but even the best doctors cannot treat the feelings of the heart.
There is no cure for my heart.
Just let it be.
It will take time for Your Highness's health to be restored.
Too much medicine is not helpful.
Your Highness can take lotus seed-core tea.
It is bitter and cold-natured
and will reduce the heat in the Heart.
Relieving internal heat will restore balance and calm,
which will benefit Your Highness.
The lotus seed-cores ... are very bitter.
Bitter is the flavor of the Heart.
Bitterness will nourish the Heart and soothe Your Highness's emotions.
"I ask the lotus why their roots are entwined"
"and why their heart is bitter."
"The two lotus flowers look towards each other fondly."
"They are a loving couple who drowned with wishes unfulfilled."
Does Your Highness remember the story?
You still remember the childhood song, Dr. Wen.
Xiao-Yunzi, where's Concubine Sourire?
My Lady is inside. Dr. Wen has come to visit her.
I will go join them.
The first time I met you,
you were on a boat collecting flowering lotus pods.
And this was the song you were singing.
When I saw you, my child's heart wished
that I would marry you when I grew up.
But I didn't know you had the wings of a phoenix.
You were not to be the wife of a humble doctor.
But seeing you like this ...
You misspeak, Dr. Wen.
I am grateful for the fondness in your heart.
Nevertheless, I have always seen you as my brother.
No more than that.
Meizhuang.
Lingrong was going to come here with me ...
but she was summoned by Her Majesty.
So I came by myself.
You ...
You should have a good rest.
My Lady.
My Lady, why did you not stay?
You look upset.
Please don't say anything like that again.
It would only lead you and I into "an abyss of no return".
Yes.
Your Highness.
Did you ask ?
Did Attendance Services send in my name tag?
They said
they could not do it
without His Majesty's permission.
But I have recovered from heatstroke ...
Does His Majesty really not want to see me anymore?
It's not that.
I asked Attendance Services.
It's not only Your Highness.
His Majesty hasn't visited any concubines recently.
He just stays at the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
No.
His Majesty is still mad at me.
But I had no intention
to cause Concubine Sourire's miscarriage.
How can His Majesty be mad at Your Highness?
His Majesty never mentioned the miscarriage again
and Your Highness has been receiving
the stipends and rewards due to a Consort.
Also, His Majesty didn't confine Your Highness.
But my honorary name was removed.
Now my rank is below the two wretches
Consort Estime and Consort Honnête.
I don't have the face to leave my palace.
His Majesty asked me to reflect on my fault.
But what did I do wrong?
Your Highness has been staying up late, one night after another.
You look unwell.
If His Majesty summons you,
you can’t meet him like this.
Really?
I look haggard?
How could I see His Majesty looking like this?
Song Zhi, do my makeup.
Forget it.
His Majesty won’t come.
Who ...
do I adorn myself for?
Sourire, you have to put your health first.
My Lady, I have the incense you asked for.
It wasn't easy to get.
Mr. Jiang had to get it from the Spice Dispensary.
He said this incense can only be used in the Palace
of Earthly Honor, by His Majesty's order.
Fortunately, Consort Nian hasn't been using a lot of it.
Lingrong, you are an expert at spices.
Please check if there’s anything strange with it.
May I use your nail guard?
It contains patchouli,
clover,
sweet pine, white sandalwood, clove
roasted agarwood
What’s wrong?
and musk.
This comes from alpine musk deer.
It is Dangmenzi - pelleted musk, not powdered.
Alpine musk deer only live in the snowy mountains of the Northwest.
It is a precious spice.
And it is ten times stronger than normal musk.
Sourire.
What is this?
Where did you get it from?
This is Pleasancy, the incense exclusively
used by the Palace of Earthly Honor.
Consort Nian has never been pregnant over the years ...
This is the real reason why.
Your pregnancy suddenly became unstable that day in her palace ...
and miscarried after kneeling for just an hour ...
Although you have a weak constitution,
without the effects of His Majesty's Pleasancy ...
Your Majesty.
You were on guard against her.
But it ended up harming our child.
Sourire, we know that women shouldn’t use musk
because it can lead to infertility.
And it can cause miscarriage or
even stillbirth.
Although I'm given to burning incense,
I would never add even a little musk.
So ...
It contains so much musk
but no one has ever noticed?
Dangmenzi has the strongest effect,
but has a light odor.
And a variety of spices have been blended into Pleasancy.
The presence of musk would go unnoticed
unless an expert closely examines it.
Why did you suspect there's something wrong with the incense?
The doctor said that I showed signs of using musk.
But after I got pregnant, I stopped using perfumes.
So I was wondering why.
This type of musk is very forceful,
and easily finds a way to enter your body.
After His Majesty left the palace,
Consort Nian frequently summoned you to her palace.
That’s why you show signs of using musk.
"When the city gate caught fire, water was drained
from the pond, leaving the fish to suffer."
I don’t even know who to blame now.
No matter if it was intentional or not.
It is all Consort Nian’s fault.
What has happened, has happened.
Don't let your thoughts dwell over it.
It is not good for restoring your health.
I see that your scar is almost invisible.
How much Scar Relief Gel is left?
Just a little.
I'm glad the gel has been so helpful.
I'm just doing what I can.
Whenever you smile,
you are still as beautiful as a flower in His Majesty's eyes.
All I can do with my sorrow is cry.
I don't look like a flower.
People in the harem who greet His Majesty with a
smile are more numerous than carp in a river.
Of course His Majesty is unwilling to step through my gloomy doors.
I spoke without thinking.
Please don't take it to heart.
His Majesty will not forget your beautiful face.
It seems that only the beautiful face
is what's unforgettable.
His Majesty hasn't visited any concubines for the past month?
Correct.
Except for visiting Your Majesty on the 15th,
His Majesty has not visited anyone else.
Have you presented the name tags to His Majesty every night?
I have, but His Majesty hasn't even bothered to look.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I was passing by your palace, so I thought I should come in.
It's very hot outside.
I hope Your Majesty wasn't affected by the summer heat.
Please have some red date tea to soothe your throat.
It's too sweet.
It has lost the flavor of tea.
I'll ask them to serve lotus seed soup instead.
It's all right.
My visit is only for a moment.
Your Majesty has slimmed down.
Are the state affairs keeping Your Majesty occupied?
Not too bad.
While Your Majesty is busy with the state affairs,
you must have someone thoughtful to serve you.
A concubine selection is arranged every three years.
With the consecutive misfortunes in the harem,
if Your Majesty feels there is no one to your liking,
we can select some new concubines to serve Your Majesty.
Concubine Sourire has just lost an imperial child,
and the Empress Dowager fell ill after hearing the news.
I lost my children and failed to fulfill my filial duty.
I'm emotionally exhausted.
How can I get in the frame of mind for a concubine selection?
I was hoping only to bring contentment to Your Majesty.
My contentment
does not come from having more women to serve me.
A woman must not only be obedient and sensible,
but also know me and understand me.
But not understand me too well,
just enough to converse intelligently with me.
Knowing me too well or too little isn't to my liking.
I understand.
It's good that you understand.
I still have things to attend to. I'll leave now.
His Majesty departs.
Your Majesty, why bother bringing up a concubine selection?
The harem never lacks concubines.
That made His Majesty unhappy.
I've never seen a man who doesn't like fresh faces.
This is even more true for an emperor.
His Majesty isn't interested in the concubines
and won't select any new ones
because he hasn't gotten over the loss of Concubine Sourire's child.
That is true.
His Majesty was never this woeful when Lady Fuca lost her child.
But His Majesty hasn't been visiting Concubine Sourire either.
Your eyes see, but your heart is not perceptive.
"The closer to home you get, the more insecure you become."
His Majesty acts like this because
he hasn't gotten over his feelings.
His Majesty said he doesn't like a woman
to understand too much about him.
I'm afraid I understand him too much.
By the way, has the doctor checked on Attendant An?
Yes, the doctor said Attendant An's throat is close to full recovery.
That's good.
Has the music instructor been teaching her?
Yes, Attendant An has been studying attentively.
Her instructor also said she is very talented.
Her voice needs more training.
It will be useful.
I lost weight after being bedridden for a month.
My Lady, you're still young.
You will make up for it.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
You still look unwell.
Have you consumed the red bird's nest Su Peisheng sent?
I have.
But nursing and nourishment take time.
The bird's nest doesn't take effect very quickly.
I notice that the scar on your neck has disappeared.
It's fortunate that it wasn't on your face.
What a shame it would be
to have "a slight blemish in pure jade".
Your Majesty dearly cherishes my face.
Huan Huan, your beauty deserves to be appreciated.
I never knew Your Majesty cares so much about my appearance.
Concubine Sourire, you're being stubborn.
I forgive you considering your recent loss.
Take some time to restore yourself.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Peace to Lady Vertu.
I'm here for the routine pulse-taking.
My Lady, what are you looking at?
Look, it's July already
but the pomegranate is still blooming
as if its flowers will bloom endlessly.
Has Concubine Sourire come here recently?
If she comes, I hope you can put away the flowers, My Lady.
They would make her sentimental.
Sir, if you see the flowers outside the palace
being harmed by the wind and the rain,
you can be the one to protect them.
But every single flower inside the palace
or even a fallen leaf,
belongs only to His Majesty.
However much you long to protect them,
you can only guard them distantly.
I understand, My Lady.
I know I don't have the blessing
to be the protector of the flower.
My only wish is to see these flowers never fading.
So my mind will be at peace.
Greedy is the human mind
which hopes to get closer one step after another.
Stop where you should
and that will go a long way.
I will obey your golden advice, My Lady.
Coua,
How do you like my singing?
I can't describe how beautiful it is.
But I think it has improved a lot from before.
That's good.
My Lady. His Majesty is there!
My Lady, shall we go greet His Majesty?
His Majesty looks unhappy.
It seems His Majesty is coming from the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I heard that Concubine Sourire has been
sad and disrespectful after her loss.
Her Highness repeatedly made His Majesty upset.
No matter what she did, she is Concubine Sourire.
How can anyone compare with her favor?
His Majesty thinks you're still recovering from your cough.
That's why he hasn't visited.
But not only you, My Lady.
His Majesty hasn't visited anyone else lately.
It doesn't matter whether His Majesty visits me or not.
The only thing I know is
that Sourire isn't anywhere near where she was before her loss.
Even Consort Nian has fallen from favor.
Now, His Majesty does not even have one concubine to his liking.
Isn't that a good thing for the palace?
Now he doesn't,
but one day he will.
When the day comes,
I hope that concubine is me.
That's for sure.
The honor and favor in the palace can't always reside in
the Palace of Earthy Honor and the Palace of Pearl Jade.
It will turn to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Since Your Majesty's trip to the Temple of Heaven,
it has rained continuously and relieved the drought.
Heaven is moved by Your Majesty's devotion.
Your Majesty has compassion for all the lives under Heaven
and Her Majesty cares for all of us concubines.
That is why we are so fortunate to admire the lotus here by Taiye Lake
I am so grateful to Your Majesty.
My proposal was approved by His Majesty.
You should thank His Majesty instead.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty accepted Lady Fuca's toast.
Please do not refuse mine.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, please have another drink.
I wish I could. I need a break.
Your Majesty is partial to Lady Fuca.
You accepted Lady Fuca's toast, but not mine.
I'm not partial to anyone.
Lady Fuca has not seen me since her miscarriage.
I am happy for her seeing that she's overcome her grief.
So I drank with her.
It sounds like His Majesty was saying that to you.
His Majesty was in a quandary about Consort Nian.
You have to understand him, Sourire.
It was my own child that I lost.
I cannot forgive even if I understand him.
Are we there yet?
Almost, Your Highness.
If everyone is attending, how could they inform me so late?
Will His Majesty want to see me?
I heard that His Majesty is very happy
about the alleviation of drought.
Since everyone is attending,
His Majesty will not embarrass Your Highness.
Your Majesty did not want to hold another Selection
so I selected some from inside the palace.
Is Your Majesty interested in meeting them?
It is a generous gesture
but I am not in the mood to do so.
It's good to gain a new, but hard to have a beloved.
The Music House rehearsed a new song.
They wish to present it to Your Majesty.
I drank too much today. I will see it another day.
They've spent a long time training
simply hoping to entertain Your Majesty.
Fine, then.
Autumn.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Peace to Consort Nian.
Rise
Your Highness will need to wait for a while.
There will be a boat to take
Your Highness to the Jade Light Island.
Her Highness is going to
the Jade Light Island by His Majesty's order.
All the concubines have traveled to the island.
They will not be able to send their boats back for now.
What about the boats for servants?
The Empress informed us that all the other boats
have been reserved for a special purpose.
That is why the lake is clear of boats at the moment.
(Lotuses are harvested south of River Yangtze)
Who is singing?
(How endless their verdant canopy expands)
Her singing is soft but skillfull.
(There’s a pair of koi fish frolicking through jade waves)
It reaches to the heart.
I like the colors in her outfit.
(They swim to the east)
A pink dress with a white lotus in green leaves.
They did put some thought into it.
The clothes are not as beautiful as her voice.
(They swim to the south)
(Who’s the girl deep in the lotus leaves?)
Why does she cover her face?
Is she too ugly to reveal it?
(Who’s the girl deep in the lotus leaves?)
To create intrigue.
(She tossed a flower pod and smiled)
Her voice is better than Lady Melodic or Attendant An's.
Even I feel soothed by her voice.
(She tossed a flower pod and smiled)
Let alone His Majesty.
Her singing isn't as good,
but it bears a remarkable resemblance ...
That is remarkable.
(Lotuses are harvested south of River Yangtze)
No one can be the same as Empress Première.
(How endless their verdant canopy expands)
Who do you think she sounds like?
She sounds rather like Lingrong.
But clearer and more skilled.
(There’s a pair of koi fish frolicking through jade waves)
Where is Lingrong? Why isn't she here?
(They swim to the east)
her cough keeps her in.
It's not unusual.
(They swim to the south)
(Who’s the girl deep in the lotus leaves?)
(She tossed a flower pod and smiled.)
Miss,
please come up here if the song is over,
at His Majesty's behest.
"Had I known beauty as such,
nothing else would I have touched."
Does Your Majesty know who she is?
Reveal your face to His Majesty.
An Lingrong bows in respect before Your Majesty.
I thought you had a cough?
Her Majesty has been taking good care of me.
I have recovered.
Not just recovered. You sing even better than before.
You put a lot of thought into this.
I'm blessed to have you as my Empress.
I saw Your Majesty was absorbed in grief
so I made this rash decision.
I hope this will bring Your Majesty joy and good health.
Mind your step.
I've never seen Her Majesty
being so devoted to His Majesty
that she sends him another woman with open arms.
Just to make him happy.
Is a loving heart as unselfish as this?
Lingrong was promoted to Attendant
around this time last year.
Now, I will promote you to Noble Lady.
I thank Your Majesty for your gracious favor.
Your Majesty, Consort Nian requests an audience.
The boats have been cleared from the lake.
Will Your Majesty send another boat to Consort Nian?
That's not necessary. Tell her to return.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Lingrong has a sweet nature.
Just the same as when you were
a new concubine in the palace.
I can't compare to a new concubine.
I'm now "old wine in a new bottle".
Your Majesty says so because you appreciate my simple nature.
Seeing you today is more inebriating than the wine.
Now that you have returned, you must sing
another song to honor your talent.
Only if Your Majesty can bear with my singing.
Cherish not your gold-woven robe, in truth.
Cherish but your golden days of youth.
Cull the flower in its full bloom,
not the empty branch you’d carry with gloom.
"Cull the flower in its full bloom."
I’ll have you as my blooming flower;
you won't feel lonely anymore.
Bring the gold-woven robe and reward it to Lady An.
Yes.
The gold-woven robe?
The prior emperor made the gold-woven robe for his Consort Serein.
Only two of them exist in the world.
One is in the palace,
and the other was taken away by Consort Serein.
It is like the poem: "The Lady arose from the lake,
beautifully adorned, as if the lake were her mirror."
"Her song of the water lilies
is worth ten thousand gold taels."
What's on your mind?
Lingrong sang this song last year in the Summer Palace
and gained favor from His Majesty.
Last year, her singing was shy and nervous.
But today, it's leisurely and confident.
That is just as well.
Lingrong has regained His Majesty’s favor.
Peace to Consort Nian.
Why are you here?
You may talk to me on the boat.
Your Highness, the boat is not for you.
I’m here to deliver His Majesty’s order.
It is inconvenient for Your Highness
to travel in the summer heat.
Your Highness should return to your palace.
You say that it is His Majesty’s order.
I will go see His Majesty myself.
Your Highness, why would I dare to deliver a false order?
His Majesty hasn't wanted to see you for more than just a day or two.
His Majesty is very pleased at the moment.
Why would you go displease him?
I don’t believe His Majesty feels no affection for the past.
"Affection for the past" stays in the past.
Now that His Majesty has a newly favored concubine,
he has no time to think about the past.
A newly favored concubine?
You mean the woman who was singing?
Your Highness surely has good hearing.
That is the newly promoted Noble Lady An.
What Noble Lady An?
She was previously Attendant An.
Your Highness,
your face became pale and sweaty under the burning sun,
and even your voice got higher.
But Lady An’s skin is soft and smooth,
and she is smiling like a flower.
Her voice is even softer than water.
Does Your Highness still think that
His Majesty will want to see you?
Your Highness, I'll take my leave now.
I'll return.
When are we going back? I want to go home.
Consort Nian came all the way here.
Why didn’t His Majesty want to see her?
Consort Honnête has long been ill
and Consort Nian fell out of favor.
His Majesty did not invite them.
Why did she come here?
She must be furious about making a futile trip.
My Lady, you should go check on her.
What can I do about her fiery temper?
Your Majesty, Wenyi is not very used to being in a new place.
May I take her back now?
Certainly.
Yes.
If Your Majesty likes Lady An's singing,
why not let her sing more songs for Your Majesty?
Sure.
I will select Lady An to stay with me tonight.
Certainly.
Here.
Peace to Your Highness.
How was His Majesty's wine?
Did you enjoy Lady An's singing?
Please don't be angry, Your Highness.
Am I angry?
Do I even dare to be angry?
His Majesty sees the smiles of the new
concubines but not the tears of the old ones.
You were all entertained at the banquet.
But I was humiliated standing in the scorching sun.
Your Highness, An was just trying to
gain His Majesty's favor with her voice.
There's no need to worry about her.
After Shen Meizhuang, there was Zhen Huan.
After Zhen Huan, here comes An Lingrong.
Each one even more bewitching than the last.
Why? Why would His Majesty favor them?
Why are you crying?
I'm the one who should be crying.
You are His Majesty's daughter.
No matter what you do wrong, he will not blame you.
But what am I to him?
He favors me when he's happy,
when he's not, he subjects me to the humiliation of others!
Cry, what is there to cry for?
Your Highness!
Wenyi is just a child. She doesn't understand anything.
Don't cry.
My child ...
If I had saved my child ...
He would also cry ... He would laugh ...
And His Majesty would never neglect me.
My child!
Your Highness, it's not the time to be sad.
If Your Highness recalls carefully,
wasn't it too odd today?
His Majesty wouldn't have informed you on short notice
and didn't summon Your Highness.
Nursemaid.
So who was it that wanted Your Highness to be there
and see Lady An's performance?
It was fortunate that
Your Highness didn't throw a tantrum about her.
Otherwise, Your Highness wouldn't be
speaking in your palace right now.
You would have been punished by His Majesty.
Yes.
I don't remember seeing the messenger eunuch before.
He said His Majesty was hosting a banquet by Taiye Lake
and asked if I would attend.
Was it Zhen Huan?
Or the Empress?
They set it up.
They all want to set me up!
This is it.
His Majesty's messengers to Your Highness
are only Mr. Su and Xiao-Xiazi.
He wouldn't send a new eunuch that you had never met.
And now we can't identify him.
But whether it was Concubine Sourire or the Empress,
Your Highness must stop being angry.
In case His Majesty hears and punishes you.
His Majesty will not see me anymore.
Why would he be offended?
It's understandable that His Majesty avoids seeing Your Highness.
Your Highness is in the "teeth of the storm".
If His Majesty treats you the same as before,
it will only cause more trouble to Your Highness.
Concubine Sourire has lost her child.
Even if Your Highness feels aggrieved,
His Majesty has to refrain from seeing you for now
to quiet down the gossip in the harem.
And if His Majesty really is mad at Your Highness,
Your Highness must avoid upsetting him.
“A separation rekindles a couple's passion.”
One day His Majesty will remember Your Highness's goodness.
Isn't that a better time to see him?
Now that I lost my position,
An has "climbed up the pole".
How despicable!
An is nobody.
She came from an unknown family.
Her freshness as a concubine is temporary.
Your Highness knows how His Majesty treats you.
How can anyone take away Your Highness's favor?
You can go now.
I will think over it.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.